Texas Governor George W. Bush:
Texas State Library and Archives Commission
Governor George W. Bush General Counsel's settlement files
1991-1996
bulk 1995-1996
Texas State Archives
Texas. Governor (1995-2000: Bush)
The Governor of the state of Texas must approve settlement of suits filed against the state. On behalf of the governor, the general counsel's office maintains these files. This series consists of memos detailing settlement offers prepared by the General Counsel for Texas Governor George W. Bush's review including, in most files, a summary of the case with the General Counsel's (GC) recommendation to accept or decline. Other items include correspondence from the Texas Attorney General and the General Counsel or Governor (usually the GC) regarding claims, judgements, orders, release of indemnity agreements, letters from the General Counsel to the Attorney General listing settlements approved by the governor, correspondence with agencies against which the claim was filed, and copies of state purchase vouchers used to pay the settlement amount to the plaintiffs. Dates of the records are 1991-1996, bulk 1995-1996. Types of claims include property damage, physical impairment, violations of the Fair Labor Standards Act, denial of unemployment benefits, medical malpractice, wrongful arrest, alleged sexual assault by co-worker, racial discrimination, and wrongful termination.
7 cubic ft.
Restrictions on Access
Because of the possibility that portions of these records fall under Public Information Act exceptions including, but not limited to, social security numbers, common law privacy (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.101); names of recipients of social services (V.T.C.A., Human Resources Code, Title 2, Section 12.003 and/or V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.101); home address and phone numbers of government employees (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.117); information created by the Texas Department of Criminal Justice (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.101 (information confidential by law, Texas Government Code, Section 508.313)); driver's license numbers, license plate numbers (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.130); results of polygraph tests (V.T.C.A., Occupations Code 1703.306); .information relating to litigation (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.103); attorney-client privilege (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.107); and agency memoranda/attorney work product (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 552.111); an archivist must review these records before they can be accessed for research. The records may be requested for research under the provisions of the Public Information Act (V.T.C.A., Government Code, Chapter 552). The researcher may request an interview with an archivist or submit a request by mail, fax, or email including enough description and detail about the information requested to enable the archivist to accurately identify and locate the information requested. If our review reveals information that may be excepted by the Public Information Act, we are obligated to seek an open records decision from the Attorney General on whether the records can be released. The Public Information Act allows the Archives ten working days after receiving a request to make this determination. The Attorney General has 45 working days to render a decision. Alternately, the Archives can inform you of the nature of the potentially excepted information and if you agree, that information can be redacted or removed and you can access the remainder of the records.
Technical Requirements
None.
Agency History
The governor of Texas is the chief executive officer of the state, elected by the citizens every four years. The duties and responsibilities of the governor include serving as commander-in-chief of the state's military forces; convening special sessions of the legislature for specific purposes; delivering to the legislature at the beginning of each regular session a report on the condition of the state, an accounting of all public money under the governor's control, a recommended biennial budget, an estimate of the amounts of money required to be raised by taxation, and any recommendations he deems necessary; signing or vetoing bills passed by the legislature; and executing the laws of the state. The governor can grant reprieves and commutations of punishment and pardons, upon the recommendation of the Board of Pardons and Paroles, and revoke conditional pardons. He appoints numerous state officials (with the consent of the Senate), fills vacancies in state and district offices (except vacancies in the legislature), calls special elections to fill vacancies in the legislature, fills vacancies in the United States Senate until an election can be held, and serves as ex officio member of several state boards.
The office of governor was first established by the Constitution of 1845 and superseded the office of president of the Republic of Texas. The position now exists under authority of Article IV, Section 1 of the Constitution of 1876 and Texas Government Code, Chapter 401. To be elected governor, a person must be at least thirty years old, a United States citizen, and a resident of Texas for at least five years preceding the election. In 1972, the term of office was extended from two to four years, effective in 1975. Since 1856 the governor has had the use of the Governor's Mansion.
In 1999 there were 198 full time equivalent employees in the Office of the Governor. Thirteen divisions outside of the Executive Office assist the governor in carrying out his functions: Administration, Appointments, Budget Planning, Communications, General Counsel, Legislative, Policy, Scheduling, Criminal Justice Division, Governor's Committee on People with Disabilities, Office of Film, Music, Television and Multimedia Industries, Women's Commission, and Texas Council on Workforce and Economic Competitiveness.
Duties of the General Counsel include providing statute interpretations; tracking inmates on death row as their cases move through the judicial process including all appeals to the governor for commutations or stays of execution; handling pardon requests sent to the governor; reviewing proposed settlements, land patents, grant requests, contracts, easements, and deeds for the governor; analyzing proposed legislation and regulations for validity and legal effect; assisting appointments staff in determining eligibility and other legal issues related to proposed appointments; handling extradition and requisition matters; coordinating ethics guidelines and training for the governor's office; advising the governor on federal programs administered by the state; coordinating the governor's criminal justice policy with the governor's Policy Director; and providing legal advice and handling litigation filed against the governor or the Governor's Office, in conjunction with actions of the Attorney General on the governor's behalf.
George W. Bush Biographical Sketch
George W. Bush served as governor of Texas from January 17, 1995 to December 21, 2000, resigning as governor in the middle of his second term to become president of the United States.
He challenged the incumbent governor, Democrat Ann Richards, running on promises to improve public education and to reform the juvenile justice system, welfare, and the state's tort laws -- the system under which an injured person may sue for damages. During the 74th Legislature in 1995, he worked with the Democrats who controlled both houses of the Texas legislature and managed to get bills passed that dealt with the four issues he had emphasized in his campaign. Bush was seen as pro-business and a consensus-builder.
Bush advocated and signed the two largest tax cuts to date in Texas history, totaling over $3 billion. To pay for the cuts, he sought (unsuccessfully) federal approval of a plan to privatize Texas' social services. Education reform was a priority throughout his terms, with legislation emphasizing local control of schools, higher standards, and a revised curriculum. Controversy has followed, with charter schools mired in financial scandals and protests against one test determining a child's promotion. After winning reelection in 1998, Bush began his bid for the presidency and was not as involved in the 76th Legislature in 1999.
George W. Bush was born July 6, 1946 in New Haven, Connecticut and grew up in Midland and Houston, Texas. He graduated from Andover Academy, and received a bachelor's degree from Yale University and a master's from Harvard Business School. He served as a pilot in the Texas Air National Guard. In 1978, Bush was defeated in a run for the U.S. Congress in West Texas. He was involved in energy exploration from the 1970s into the 1980s. From 1989 until his election as governor, Bush worked with the Texas Rangers baseball organization, leading a group of partners in purchasing the team, and then serving as managing general partner. He married Laura Welch in 1977; they have two daughters.
Scope and Contents of the Records
The Governor of the state of Texas must approve settlement of suits filed against the state. On behalf of the governor, the general counsel's office maintains these files. This series consists of memos detailing settlement offers prepared by the General Counsel for Texas Governor George W. Bush's review including, in each file, a summary of the case with the General Counsel's (GC) recommendation to accept or decline. Other items include correspondence from the Texas Attorney General and the General Counsel or Governor (usually the GC) regarding claims, judgements, orders, release and settlement agreements, letters from the General Counsel to the Attorney General listing settlements approved by the governor, correspondence with agencies whom the claim was filed against, and copies of state purchase vouchers used to pay the settlement amount to the plaintiffs. Dates of the records are 1991-1996, bulk 1995-1996. There are a few files containing correspondence between the agency and the general counsel concerning a settlement offer by the plaintiff that the agency declined to accept. In these few cases, there may be notes on the letter or a memo from the general counsel to indicate the GC's acknowledgement and/or actions taken.
Claims were submitted by either individuals or companies. Types of claims include property damage, physical impairment, violations of the Fair Labor Standards Act, denial of unemployment benefits, medical malpractice, wrongful arrest, alleged sexual assault by co-worker, racial discrimination, wrongful termination, and use of excessive force against inmates in the state's prison system. The governor's decision is not noted in these records. The memos where the governor checks 'accept' or 'deny' and signs the offer are in the series Legal opinions and advice (settlement files). This series is also where what settlement records exist for 1997-2000 can be found. It is possible files for this period may still be at the current governor's office.
An inventory of settlement files was prepared for each box by the governor's staff. The inventories list the files in either reverse chronological order or chronological order, by date of the settlement memo to the governor and are filed preceeding the files listed for that box.
An item level index to portions of the General Counsel's records, created by the Governor's Office, is available on CD ROM. Contact Texas State Archives staff for assistance.
This finding aid describes one series of Texas Governor George W. Bush's records. See
Texas Governor George W. Bush: An Overview of Records
for more records series. If you are reading this electronically, click on the link to go to the finding aid. If you are reading this in the Archives Reading Room, the overall finding aid is found at a separate divider within the binder.
Arrangement of the Records
These records are organized into three groups as received from the Governor's Office - Group one settlement files, January-October 1995; Group two settlement files, January 1995-July 1996; and Group three settlement files, April-September 1996. The dates of the group reflect the dates of the settlement memos, not necessary the dates of all the documents within the files. Within the first two groups the files are arranged in alphabetical order. Records in the last group are in reverse chronological order by date of the memo to the governor.
Index Terms
The terms listed here were used to catalog the records. The terms can be used to find similar or related records.
Corporate Names:
Texas. Office of the Governor. General Counsel.
Subjects:
Government attorneys--Texas.; Torts--Texas.; Medical personnel--Malpractice--United States.
Places:
Texas--Politics and government--1951-
Document Types:
Correspondence--Texas--Governors--1991-1996 (bulk 1995-1996).; Memoranda--Texas--Governors--1991-1996 (bulk 1995-1996).; Judicial records--Texas--Governors--1991-1996 (bulk 1995-1996).; Legal documents--Texas--Governors--1991-1996 (bulk 1995-1996).
Functions:
Advising Texas governors.
Related Material
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the agencies and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Texas State Archives
Texas Governor George W. Bush, General Counsel's legal opinions and advice, 1892, 1918, 1921, 1925, 1932, 1942-1944, 1948, 1954, 1956, 1963, 1965, 1968-1969, 1972-2000 (bulk 1995-2000), 14 cubic ft.
Texas Governor George W. Bush, General Counsel's claims against the state, 1990-2000 (bulk 1995-2000), 3.6 cubic ft.
Accession Information
Accession number: 2002/151
In December 2000, Governor George W. Bush designated the George Bush Presidential Library as the repository for the records from his tenure as Governor of Texas, under authority of Texas Government Code, Section 441.201. Shortly after he left office, the records were shipped to the Bush Library in College Station, Texas. Texas Attorney General John Cornyn ruled the records are state records subject to the Texas Public Information Act and the management of the Texas State Library and Archives Commission even after transfer to a federal facility (Opinion No. JC-0498, May 3, 2002). In July 2002 the records were transferred from the Bush Library to the Texas State Archives in Austin for preparation for research use. In June 2003, a memorandum of understanding signed by representatives of the National Archives and Records Administration, the Texas State Library and Archives Commission, and George W. Bush replaced a January 2002 interim memorandum of understanding. The records will be returned to the Bush Library after the project has been completed.
Detailed Description of the Records
- Governor George W. Bush General Counsel's settlement files, 1991-1996, bulk 1995-1996, 7 cubic ft.
  Most folders in this series contain information that may be excepted from public disclosure because of certain permissive or mandatory exceptions, including Comptroller payee numbers on purchase vouchers (552.147); Attorney General memos and letters containing confidential information, attorney-client privilege, attorney-work product, or litigation information (552.101; 552.103; 552.107; 552.111); and Governor's Office memos or letters containing attorney-client privilege or inter-/intra-agency information (552.107; 552.111). Because these possible exceptions are found throughout the records, they are not noted within the folder listing. However, other Public Information Act exceptions to disclosure are noted. Upon receipt of a public information request, creating agencies will review responsive documents to determine if they wish to assert permissive exceptions under the Public Information Act.
  - Group one settlement files, January-October 1995
    - Box one inventory (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Acosta, Ramon vs. University of Texas (UT), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - AFEX Corporation vs. Mark Holtzapple, et al, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Aguayo, Patti, vs. Texas Youth Commission (TYC), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Alcon, Armand vs. Texas Water Development Board, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Alfred, Louis and Michels, Judy vs. Texas A M University System, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Allied Parcel Service vs. Texas Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation (MHMR), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Almaza, Mayela vs. Texas Department of Public Safety (DPS), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - AMC Industries, Inc. vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - American Indemnity vs. General Services Commission (GSC), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Anderson, Ferman vs. Texas Youth Commission (TYC), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Apadoca, Leslie vs. University of Texas Medical Branch, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Apadoca, Luis vs. Texas Tech Health Sciences Center, 1992-1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Arellano, G. vs. Texas House of Representatives, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Armstrong, Louis vs. Texas State Board of Barber Examiners, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Arrendondo, Price vs. Texas Department of Commerce, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Ashman, Harry M. and James Meyers vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Ayala, Genoneva, et al. vs. MHMR, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy - name of patient in state mental hospital] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Barker, Andrea vs. Texas A M University System, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Bednar, Dee vs. Lionell Meno, et al, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Benson, Ned vs. Texas Department of Human Services (DHS) and Texas Department of Protective and Regulatory Services (TDPRS), 1993-1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Biggs, Harry vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Bodiford vs. DHS, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy - name of recipient of social services] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Braig, Edward vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Braig, Edward vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Brawley, Carlton vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Bray, Charlie vs. General Land Office, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Brooks, Linda vs. Jim Lehrman, et al, 1992-1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Brown, Kathleen vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Brown, Larry, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Brown, Tammy vs. DPS and James Rand, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Brownloe, Duane and Theresa vs. Bristol -Myers Squibb Co., et al, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Bunton, Terry vs. Railroad Commission of Texas, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Cabera, Luz vs. TYC, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Caballero, Phyllis, et al. vs. Texas Department of Criminal Justice (TDCJ), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Calvert, Beverly vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Cantu, Amelia vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Carisalez vs. Texas Funeral Service Commission, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Castaneda, Joe vs. TYC, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Castecka, John vs. DPS, 1994-1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Castelan, et al, vs. Burton Raiford and DHS, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy - name of recipient of social services] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Caston Company vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Chavera vs. DHS, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Chick, Anthony Christopher vs. Texas A M University System, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Christofoletti, Ron vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Cofer, Steve vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Coleman, Ruthie and Tommy vs. State, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Coleman, Subrina vs. University of Houston, Central Campus, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Cope, Bonnie and Keith vs. University of Texas MD Anderson, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Corley, Pamela va. TDCJ, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Cornelius, Arthur vs. DHS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Coventon, James vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Cross, Bobby, et al. vs. TxDOT, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Crowson, Noel vs. TDPRS, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Culberson, Bobbie, et al. vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Daniels, Lee vs. Texas A M University System, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Davis, Burl vs. Gtech, Inc. and Texas Comptroller of Public Accounts, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Davis, Willie and Raymond vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Del Rio, Frank vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Doak, Richard and Elsa vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Doe, John vs. Joshua Mora, 1994-1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Doe, John vs. Joshua Mora, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Dubinski, Larry vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Enterprise Rent A Car vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Evans vs. Eldridge, 1994-1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Evans, Melissa vs. TYC, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Fabling, Loretta and R. vs. Texas Parks and Wildlife Department (TPWD), 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Fance, Erica vs. DHS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Felco Auto Leasing vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Fernandez, Lydia vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Fisher, Barbara Word vs. University of Texas at Austin (UT Austin), 1994-1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Flink, J.B. vs. Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Flores, Janet and Erasmo vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Flores, Yolanda vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Foster, Barbara vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Friel, Tina vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gale, John vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Galindo, Aldred and Yolanda vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Galindo, Guadalupe vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gallagher, Michael vs. TDCJ, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gallimore, Gene vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gaona, Benjamin and Beatriz vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Garcia, M. and Alvardo, Juan A. vs. University of Texas, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: attorney work product] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Garcia, Maren and Juan Alvardo vs. Harris County Hospital District, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: attorney work product] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Garnite Roofing Corporation and Union Standard Insurance Co. vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gartman, Joe vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gates, Frances vs. DPS, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gause, Thomas X. vs. TDCJ, 1994-1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: social security number, common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - General Services Commission, Texas Department of Agriculture and Hardy Properties, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gills vs. University of Houston, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Goe Environmental vs. Texas A M University, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gonzales, Valentine vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gonzalez, Susana vs. Albert Benson and TYC, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Gonzalez, Susana vs. TYC, 1995, [Contains possibly excepted information: common law privacy] (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Goggan, Tammy vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Goodrum, Charlene and Garland vs. TDCJ, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Graham, April vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Green, Sheila and Clara Hardaway vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Griggs, Debbie vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)
    - Grimes, George and Kenneth Brown vs. MHMR, 1995 (Box 2002/151-322)